{"tossups": [{"question": "This battle occurred after one side ignored the advice of Mikhail Kutuzov to retreat into Carpathia, after being defeated during the Ulm Campaign. The winning commander here strategically deployed below the Pratzen Heights, only to retake them later in a daring charge. Its aftermath led to the creation of the Confederation of the Rhine and the dissolution of the Holy Roman Empire. For the point, name this 1805 victory by Napoleon over the forces of Austria and Russia.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Austerlitz</b> (accept Battle of the<b> Three Emperors</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "After this leader was defeated by an invading army led by Rodolfo Graziani in 1935, he protested the use of chemical weapons in that war in a speech at the League of Nations. After this leader\u2019s death, the Derg military junta took power. Eritrea was annexed under the leadership of this man, whose 1966 arrival in Jamaica is celebrated on Grounation Day. For the point, name this long-reigning Emperor of Ethiopia and messiah of the Rastafari movement.", "answer": "<b> Haile Selassie</b> I", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In this country, the practice of speaking in tongues was revived in the 1906 Azusa Street Revival. A religious movement founded in this country publishes a magazine called<em> The Watchtower</em>, and another religious movement in this country believes that all matter is illusory. One man in this country founded a religion after he claimed to translate golden plates shown to him by the angel Moroni. For the point, name this country where Joseph Smith founded the Latter Day Saint movement.", "answer": "<b> U</b>nited<b> S</b>tates of America (accept<b> America</b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Tahir ibn Husayn laid siege to this city after his victory at the Battle of Rayy, which was fought during a civil war for the control of this city between the brothers Al-Amin and Al-Ma\u2019mun. The mathematician al-Khwarizmi worked in this city\u2019s House of Wisdom. Al-Mustasim failed to defend this city from invaders in 1258, after which he was trampled in a carpet on the orders of Hulagu Khan, who led the Mongol sack of this city. For the point, name this former seat of the Abbasid Caliphate and modern capital of Iraq.", "answer": "<b> Baghdad</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This ruler\u2019s predecessor, Abu Bakr II, disappeared after exploring a \u201criver with a powerful current,\u201dthe Atlantic Ocean. The lower level of this man\u2019s \u201cHall of Audience\u201d was plated in gold. The Sankore Madrasah was built during this man\u2019s rule and had the largest collection of books in Africa after the Library of Alexandria. This man brought 23 camels laden with gold dust on his 1324 hajj to Mecca, devaluing gold throughout North Africa. For the point, name this wealthy Mansa of the Mali Empire.", "answer": "Mansa<b> Musa</b> I", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This country underwent two School Wars regarding the role of religion in education. A king of this country employed Henry Morton Stanley and a group which cut off the hands of those who didn\u2019t meet rubber quotas, the<em> Force Publique</em>. This country was ruled by kings like Albert II and another who was criticized by Roger Casement, Leopold II. The headquarters of the European Union is located in, for the point, what country whose capital is Brussels?", "answer": "<b> Belgium</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One man with this last name successfully argued the case<em> Sweatt v. Painter</em> while leading the Legal Defense Fund. A judge with this surname sustained the sanctity of contracts in<em> Dartmouth College v.</em> <em>Woodward</em> and struck down state taxation of the Second Bank of the U.S. in<em> McCulloch v. Maryland</em>. This was the last name of the first African-American justice on the Supreme Court. For the point, give this shared last name of Supreme Court Justices John and Thurgood.", "answer": "(Thurgood and/or John)<b> Marshall</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "In 1968, oil was discovered in this state\u2019s Prudhoe Bay. The majority of this state\u2019s population lives in a region known as the Railbelt, as it is centered on a railroad that passes through Deadhorse and Gold Creek. This state\u2019s largest cargo port lies on the Knik Arm of the Cook Inlet and suffered greatly during the 1964 Good Friday earthquake. Former senator Ted Stevens names the largest airport in this state, where an annual race extends over 1,000 miles to Nome. For the point, name this state where the Iditarod sled dog race begins in Anchorage.", "answer": "<b> Alaska</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This ruler signed the Eternal Peace, which lasted only eight years after fighting resumed in the Lazic War over parts of Georgia. This man\u2019s wars against Khosrau I of the Sassanid Empire were temporarily halted due to a plague historically named for him. This ruler employed Belisarius to retake Carthage and Rome. This emperor managed to put down the Nika riots at the urging of his wife Theodora. For the point, name this Byzantine emperor whose law code became the basis of Western law.", "answer": "<b> Justinian the Great</b> (or<b> Justinian I</b>; prompt on Justinian)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A leader of this group later became Governor of Upper Louisiana and died a mysterious death along the Natchez Trace trail. The only casualty among this group was Charles Floyd, whose appendix ruptured. This group constructed Fort Clatsop to winter in Oregon, and established relations with tribes like the Mandan. The slave York and the Shoshone [sho-SHO-nee] woman Sacajawea were companions of, for the point, what early 19th century expedition to explore the Louisiana Purchase and reach the Pacific Ocean?", "answer": "<b> Lewis and Clark</b> expedition (accept<b> Corps of Discovery</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man married the princess Roxana shortly after capturing a fortress known as the Sogdian Rock. This man constructed a causeway to attack an island fortress and end the Siege of Tyre. This man named a city for his horse, Bucephalus, following the Battle of the Hydaspes [hi-dass-peez], and he defeated a force twice his size outside the city of Issus. Darius III was repeatedly beaten by, for the point, what Macedonian ruler who conquered Persia and was the son of Philip II?", "answer": "<b> Alexander the Great</b> (or<b> Alexander III</b> of Macedon; prompt on Alexander)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "After this commander\u2019s men led a successful campaign through Kernstown and Winchester in the Shenandoah Valley, they were exhausted and generally ineffective during the Seven Days\u2019 Battles. At First Bull Run, this man\u2019s troops stood their ground on Henry House Hill, a key turning point in the Confederate victory. At the Battle of Chancellorsville, this subordinate of Robert E. Lee was mortally wounded by friendly fire. For the point, name this Confederate Lieutenant General nicknamed \u201cStonewall.\u201d", "answer": "Stonewall<b> Jackson</b> (or Thomas (Jonathan)<b> Jackson</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Mines in this modern country supplied most of the uranium for the Manhattan Project; that mining industry was centered on this country\u2019s city of Elisabethville, now known as Lubumbashi, the capital of its Katanga Province. This modern-day country suffered two decades of personal rule under King Leopold II, after which it was transfered to the Belgian parliament\u2019s control. For the point, name this modern-day African country whose capital is Kinshasa.", "answer": "<b> D</b>emocratic<b> R</b>epublic of the<b> C</b>ongo (prompt on Congo; do not accept or prompt on \u201cRepublic of (the) Congo\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Howard Hawks directed a 1932 film about this man subtitled \u201cThe Shame of a Nation.\u201d Robert De Niro played this man in a 1987 Brian de Palma film in which he is the target of the Kevin Costner-played Eliot Ness,<em> The Untouchables</em>. This man deteriorated from syphilis during the seven years he spent in prison for tax evasion. This man\u2019s operatives killed seven members of Bugs Moran\u2019s rival gang in the Saint Valentine\u2019s Day Massacre. For the point, name this prohibition-era gangster who led the Chicago Outfit.", "answer": "Alphonse \u201cAl\u201d<b> Capone</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country\u2019s New Academy sought public voting, and its founder Alexandra Pascalidou advocated for \u201copen and inclusive\u201d ideals, in the wake of a 2018 scandal. Sara Danius stepped down as the first female head of a group in this nation in response to scandals involving its self-proclaimed \u201c19th member\u201d and Katarina Frostenson. Accusations that Jean-Claude Arnault sexually assaulted women led to a committee cancelling the awarding of the 2018 Nobel Prize in Literature in, for the point, what Scandinavian country?", "answer": "<b> Sweden</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "In this Asian country, Kermit Roosevelt oversaw the CIA\u2019s Operation Ajax, which orchestrated the overthrow of prime minister Mohammad Mosaddegh. The White Revolution brought land reform and modernization to this country, but ended in 1979 in an Islamic revolution. During the 1980s, the U.S. government sold arms to factions in this country to send money to the Nicaraguan Contras. For the point, name this country where a hostage crisis erupted after the capture of the U.S. embassy in Tehran.", "answer": "<b> Iran</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A song about this man derived its tune from \u201cSay, Brothers, Will You Meet Us;\u201d that song about this man was later used by Julia Ward Howe as the melody for \u201cThe Battle Hymn of the Republic.\u201dHarriet Tubman helped this man recruit soldiers for an attack on an armory that was put down by forces under Robert E. Lee. For the point, name this abolitionist who was hanged after failing to capture Harper\u2019s Ferry.", "answer": "John<b> Brown</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The general Cao Qin [sow chin] rebelled against this dynasty following the Tumu Crisis. This dynasty waged the Imjin War against Japan under the Wanli emperor. One emperor reorganized this dynasty\u2019s government to consist of a single Grand Secretariat and Six Ministries; that ruler, the Yongle Emperor, also dispatched the expeditions of Zheng He [huh]. For the point, name this Chinese dynasty that collapsed in 1644 and is famous today for its porcelain pottery.", "answer": "<b> Ming</b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}